<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Ewelina Stepien&#39;s blog</title>
<link>https://estepien.netlify.app/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://estepien.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.475</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>My career transition journey</title>
  <dc:creator>Ewelina Stepien</dc:creator>
  <link>https://estepien.netlify.app/posts/introduction/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After reading blog posts about other people’s transition to data analytics and coding, I thought that it would be a good idea reflect on my own journey in the first post on my blog.</p>
<p>Although I officially started to learn coding in R in 2022, I have been telling stories using data since 2017.</p>
<hr>
<section id="first-steps-in-data-analysis-and-statistics" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="first-steps-in-data-analysis-and-statistics">1. First steps in data analysis and statistics</h4>
<p>I had always been fascinated with human behaviour, therefore deciding to study psychology was a natural choice for me.</p>
<p>While completing my undergraduate degree in psychology at the Manchester Metropolitan University, I was a member of a research club within the department and learnt about the basics of statistics and data analysis. Despite enjoying data analysis in IBM SPSS as a part of my course, I felt that managing larger data set was difficult and geenrated data visualisations looked slightly boring.</p>
<p>Although I first heard about R and Python around 2018, my busy university schedule and part-time work did not allow me to explore these matters further.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-management-in-a-professional-setting" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-management-in-a-professional-setting">2. Data management in a professional setting</h4>
<p>I completed my undergraduate degree in 2020 and, as ‘the pandemic class’ graduate, I decided to gain work experience. In autumn 2020, I secured a remote role as a student services advisor in a financial education company. In this role, I learnt how to manage personal and financial data using an enterprise resource planning software, namely Microsoft Dynamics NAV, and advanced the skills I already had, such as Microsoft Excel.</p>
</section>
<section id="back-in-academia" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="back-in-academia">3. Back in academia</h4>
<p>Despite enjoying the student advisor role, I decided to continue my education. In autumn 2021, I started a full-time master of science degree in clinical and health psychology at the University of Manchester. Handling multiple deadlines made me think about ways to make my coursework preparation more efficient. I was motivated to not only shorten the time I spend on analysing data for reports, but also making them look more professional and engaging.</p>
<p>This motivation led me to learning the basics of LaTeX and VSCode to complete a major assignment involving several photos with captions. Using these tools allowed me to easily apply a consistent formatting style to all elements of the report, which made preparing it much more enjoyable and quicker.</p>
<p>Shortly after submitting it, I came across videos about creating plots in R using the ggplot2 package. I immediately liked the idea of organising and visualising data using just a few quick commands. After watching several screencasts of Tidy Tuesday data analysis, I decided to finally give it a try myself.</p>
<p>Although my very first attempts at executing codes were not always successful and sometimes I was overwhelmed by error messages, I also felt extremely proud of myself once I was able to fix the issues and generate my first data visualisation/table in R (and then the second, then the third…).</p>
</section>
<section id="what-now" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-now">4. What now?</h4>
<p>After completing my postgraduate degree in winter 2022, I decided to fully dedicate my time to pursue a career in data analytics instead of psychology.</p>
<p>Despite re-evaluating my career plans, I still consider my two degrees as invaluable experience. Both courses provided me with strong research skills and statistical knowledge, which definitely makes understanding coding and data science easier. In particular, my masters degree showed me that making sense of data is something I enjoy the most and therefore I should pursue further.</p>
<p>Since graduating from the university in December 2022, I have:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Finished studying the amazing book called ‘R for Data Science (2e)’ by Hadley Wickam and colleagues</strong>. Although I used <a href="https://r4ds.hadley.nz/">the free online resources</a> provided by the authors, I also have a physical copy of the first edition of the book. I found these materials helpful in not only learning about the good habits in coding (such as using <a href="https://style.tidyverse.org/">the tidyverse style guide</a> and importance of leaving comments explaining my thought process) but also making me more confident about handling not very ‘clean’ data.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Set up my GitHub account and learnt how to use Git.</strong> In the beginning of my coding journey, I felt quite overwhelmed by navigating in Git and uploading my work from local to remote repositories on GitHub. Just a couple of weeks later, I feel confident in using Git and sometimes even use logs as a time machine if something goes wrong! While my GitHub portfolio is still small, I am excited and motivated to grow it (especially now that I know how to keep my projects safe and organised).</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Although it is still the beginning of my data analytics journey, I am definitely keen on continuing it!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>career transition</category>
  <category>psychology</category>
  <category>self-study</category>
  <guid>https://estepien.netlify.app/posts/introduction/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
